<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>All Things Gameplay</title><link>https://demo.stack.jimmycai.com/</link><description>Recent content on All Things Gameplay</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 17 May 2025 21:47:24 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://demo.stack.jimmycai.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Cereal Time Blocking: Where Flexibility Meets Structure</title><link>https://demo.stack.jimmycai.com/p/cereal-time-blocking-where-flexibility-meets-structure/</link><pubDate>Sat, 17 May 2025 21:47:24 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://demo.stack.jimmycai.com/p/cereal-time-blocking-where-flexibility-meets-structure/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="how-i-manage-my-tasks-and-time-for-both-school-and-gamedev">How I manage my tasks and time for both school and gamedev
&lt;/h1>&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve tried many ways to organize my work over my life, and today I will
share a flexible yet thoughtful methodology. &lt;em>In my opinion at least.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The first step is to time block tasks.
Time blocking means planning a task over a specific period of time.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The importance of time blocking is to &lt;strong>not overbook&lt;/strong> yourself. It&amp;rsquo;s also
a good practice for &lt;strong>estimating&lt;/strong> workload, and &lt;strong>measuring&lt;/strong> whether or not you&amp;rsquo;re
late on your schedule on a daily basis.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You may ask: &amp;ldquo;Is that all?&amp;rdquo;.&lt;br>
The thing is, time blocking lacks flexibility. You have an urgency ?
&lt;strong>Poof&lt;/strong>, time blocking is cooked.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you did time blocking well, you know how much time you want to work, and
which tasks you want to do. Now, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter really much &lt;strong>exactly&lt;/strong>
when a task is completed &lt;em>usually&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>That&amp;rsquo;s when the serial planning becomes &lt;strong>cereal&lt;/strong> instead. By taking into account
&lt;em>mishaps&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Also, it lowers the tendency of the mind to over optimize your
schedule for no reason. For me, it also feels more natural, as I find it
stressful and non-natural to &lt;strong>always&lt;/strong> follow strictly your schedule.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Simply put, time blocking task gives you an overview of the workload at hand, and keeps you on track.&lt;br>
Because you can&amp;rsquo;t plan for everything, it&amp;rsquo;s better sometimes to approximately follow the schedule, and change the order of tasks.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>TLDR; Put the milk before the cereal.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Data Assets and Scriptable Objects as First Stepping Stones toward Data Oriented Development</title><link>https://demo.stack.jimmycai.com/p/data-assets-and-scriptable-objects-as-first-stepping-stones-toward-data-oriented-development/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 12:21:27 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://demo.stack.jimmycai.com/p/data-assets-and-scriptable-objects-as-first-stepping-stones-toward-data-oriented-development/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="how-the-usage-daso-can-help-your-development-process">How the usage DA/SO can help your development process
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>I frequently use &lt;a class="link" href="https://docs.unity3d.com/6000.0/Documentation/Manual/class-ScriptableObject.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Scriptable Objects&lt;/a> in Unity and &lt;a class="link" href="https://dev.epicgames.com/documentation/en-us/unreal-engine/data-assets-in-unreal-engine" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Data Assets&lt;/a> in Unreal to help the design team.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Essentially, instead of telling them to modify some variable in the
code, I tell them to modify some variable in a specific file, either the
DA or SO.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s nice for them because :&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>It&amp;rsquo;s way &lt;strong>simpler&lt;/strong>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>All related data are &lt;strong>bundled&lt;/strong> together.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>They can make &amp;ldquo;backups&amp;rdquo; of the file in order to &lt;strong>test new things&lt;/strong>
and safely come back to the previous values.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s nice for me because I can focus on &lt;strong>developing new systems&lt;/strong>, and I can
easily make changes to the codebase &lt;strong>without worrying&lt;/strong> about the designers
getting lost after all that Friday night refactoring.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>My workflow goes on like this :&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>First, I program the system.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Then, I abstract the data used into a DA/SO.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Finally, I explain to the designer where is the new DA/SO and what it is
responsible for.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s simple, and can have many advantages even for the &lt;strong>gameplay itself&lt;/strong>.
For example, you might want to have an easy or hard mode. Just make an
easy and a hard SO/DA. Just feed the right data.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In that regard, I think it is a good first step into data driven gameplay,
by enabling designers and artists to customize gameplay elements
just by changing data.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>What is the Ubisoft Gamelab, and why it is important.</title><link>https://demo.stack.jimmycai.com/p/what-is-the-ubisoft-gamelab-and-why-it-is-important./</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 May 2025 20:07:27 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://demo.stack.jimmycai.com/p/what-is-the-ubisoft-gamelab-and-why-it-is-important./</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://demo.stack.jimmycai.com/p/what-is-the-ubisoft-gamelab-and-why-it-is-important./CUBI_Banner.jpg" alt="Featured image of post What is the Ubisoft Gamelab, and why it is important." />&lt;h2 id="about-the-gamelab">About the Gamelab
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>The Gamelab is essentially a &lt;strong>game jam spanning across 10 weeks&lt;/strong>.
Usually, a theme and 3 constraints are imposed on the contenders.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Each team can have up to &lt;strong>8 members&lt;/strong>. Also, all the teams must be associated
with a university in Québec (the province, not the city). Though members
can be from other universities too, which is great !&lt;/p>
&lt;p>On top of that, each team has &lt;strong>two mentors&lt;/strong> who work at Ubisoft. Very useful.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In terms of scale, the 2025 Gamelab had &lt;strong>206 participants&lt;/strong> shared by &lt;strong>12
universities&lt;/strong>. The Gamelab ends with a boot, followed by a gala, where
prizes based on 9 categories are given.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="my-2024-participation">My 2024 participation
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve participated in the 2024 and the 2025 edition of the Ubisoft Gamelab.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>My university is not very gamedev oriented (even though things are getting
better in that regard), and I basically learned about the 2024 Gamelab
&lt;strong>the same day&lt;/strong> the teams were required to be confirmed.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It was a butthead decision, but the teacher responsible for the
process was super understanding. We were originally 3 when we talked to him.
So I started my search for 5 other members.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The first 2 others were pretty easy to find, just two other (great)
programmer friends. But now, I had to find artists and a designer.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I was spamming emails all over the place. I was so lucky to stumble upon
two great artists, and one nice designer.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You see, there isn&amp;rsquo;t a ton of game universities with a program
specialized in video game art. It just so happened that the &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.nad.ca/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>&lt;strong>NAD&lt;/strong>&lt;/a>
was just in front of my university. It just so happened that a lot
of people in this school want to do the UbiGamelab, but can&amp;rsquo;t
(especially freshmen).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Thus, thee found the freshman art makers and the game designer&lt;/em>.
&lt;br>(he was from &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.uqat.ca/etudes/creation-et-nouveaux-medias/baccalaureat-en-creation-de-jeux-video/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>&lt;strong>UQAT&lt;/strong>&lt;/a> though, but the same logic applies).&lt;/p>
&lt;img src="foule_gamelab_2024.png" alt="Picture of the 2024 edition crowd" width="80%" style="display:block;margin-left:auto; margin-right:auto"/>
&lt;p>We were very inexperienced and one of the constraints was to make a
online multiplayer game. It was a grind, managing both finals and
the last minute sprint to ship the game. It was more importantly a blast !&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We did end up being nominated in the game design category, which was
unexpected and very appreciated.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m still &lt;strong>very&lt;/strong> grateful to my team and my mentors for this journey.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="my-2025-participation">My 2025 participation
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>I got to be honest, the stars kind of aligned for me to participate in
the 2025 edition. I was encouraged by my teacher, I had made a promise to
another participant, and one of the artists, that I
worked with during the 2024 edition, just came to me with 4 of his friends.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Let&amp;rsquo;s say that it was &lt;em>wayyyy&lt;/em> easier to make a team this time.
I didn&amp;rsquo;t get to choose the programmers I was going to work with this time,
and it was for the better. Both of them are great programmers, and I&amp;rsquo;m
grateful that I had the chance to work with such &lt;strong>great teammates&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This time around though, we were balling. We chose Unreal 5 for our engine,
as the artists were more used to it. The team had more overall gamedev and
jams experience.&lt;/p>
&lt;img src="foule_gamelab_2025.jpg" alt="Picture of the 2025 edition crowd" width="80%" style="display:block;margin-left:auto; margin-right:auto"/>
&lt;p>It ended up as a smoother and more productive process. We felt really
proud about the artistic direction and the amount of polish we had achieved.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Despite that, we sadly didn&amp;rsquo;t turn out to win. Let&amp;rsquo;s say it was more of a
critical success than a commercial one.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="positive-outcomes">Positive outcomes
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>You will make friends. Great friends. It&amp;rsquo;s a good opportunity to connect
with current / future industry workers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Not only that, it&amp;rsquo;s not everyday we can work on a big project
with specialized people as a student. Working alongside designers and
artists is a very different &lt;strong>(much better)&lt;/strong> experience.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Let&amp;rsquo;s be honest, it kind of looks good on the resume. I think it has
helped me to get into a master&amp;rsquo;s in game programming. A discussion for
another time.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It is a learning opportunity, for both hard skills and soft skills.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Lastly, it is super &lt;strong>fun&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="negative-outcomes">Negative outcomes
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>The Gamelab is a &lt;strong>huge&lt;/strong> time investment and it will impact your grades.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It can be very stressful at times, as y&amp;rsquo;all as a team are very likely
to have some hurdles.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>By the way, I don&amp;rsquo;t think the Gamelab is a good place
to acquire new knowledge. It&amp;rsquo;s more appropriate to test
the knowledge you already have. In short, I would advise &lt;strong>against&lt;/strong>
learning gamedev for the first time there.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="advice">Advice
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>I think communication is key. As basic as it might sound, getting to know
your colleagues before and during the competition will grease the engine.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For a less basic advice, the prototype is a way to communicate
with your colleagues. Everybody will have an idea about how the game
is, being able to test ideas and show some concrete examples will greatly
help. &lt;strong>Build often&lt;/strong>, and send it to everyone on the team. Test the game
during your meeting.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As for the mentors, you should meet them at the same time. Each will bounce
back on what the other said, and it will be more fruitful that way.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Scope management will hinder or bring your success. Be flexible, and
pick your battle. Feedback is good based on the content &lt;strong>and&lt;/strong> the timing
of when it is given.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Make a retrospective at the end of the project. You can do it on your own,
but with your team it would be great. It is very educational, as you will
get to know blind spots.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If possible, choosing one or two easier classes might help. You still
have to be a full-time student to participate.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>I think it&amp;rsquo;s important to talk about such subjects, as not everybody knows
about such events, or the possibility to make such events.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I &lt;strong>highly&lt;/strong> suggest anybody invested in gamedev to participate. If you
don&amp;rsquo;t have something similar in your area, use the Gamelab as an example
to your local companies ! Employees love to give back to the community,
it&amp;rsquo;s great for the brand, and maybe it&amp;rsquo;s good to find new hires.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Hope it was a good read !&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Welcome to my game programming blog !</title><link>https://demo.stack.jimmycai.com/p/welcome-to-my-game-programming-blog/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 18:47:27 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://demo.stack.jimmycai.com/p/welcome-to-my-game-programming-blog/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="bonjour--hi-">Bonjour / Hi !
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>My name is &lt;strong>Raphaël&lt;/strong>, and I&amp;rsquo;m currently finishing my &lt;a class="link" href="https://etudier.uqam.ca/programme?code=7316" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>CS degree at UQÀM&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Not only have I always thought that blogs were &lt;em>couwl&lt;/em>, I find gamedev related blogs and devlogs to be even &lt;em>couwler&lt;/em>.
That&amp;rsquo;s one of the many reasons pushing me to write markdown on a Tuesday night.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The thing is, I found there was a lack for a particular type of blog, then
it was settled that I had to take care of the matter.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-this-blog-is-about-">What this blog is about ?
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>The main topic of this blog is gamedev, more precisely &lt;strong>gameplay programming&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We can find a lot of blogs about many topics in gamedev, but I found it
way too hard to look for blogs centered around gameplay programming, despite
being one of the most important pillars in game development.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Also, I found that most bloggers were super experienced principal experts, which I love.&lt;br>
&lt;em>But&lt;/em>, I also think that having a blog hosted by another upcoming dev, dealing with
both studies and game development could be a nice refresher.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>TLDR; &lt;strong>gameplay programming&lt;/strong> with a little sugarcoat of slice of life and fun gaming facts.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="my-game-projects">My game projects
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>Classified from the most recent to the oldest. Also, not including all game jams.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="urban-strikers">Urban Strikers
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>A versus sport game with a visually &lt;em>Jet Set Radio&lt;/em> vibe and a gameplay-wise &lt;em>Rocket League&lt;/em> &amp;amp; &lt;em>Knockout City&lt;/em> vibe.&lt;br>
I&amp;rsquo;ve mostly worked as a programmer on the gameloop, UI and player movement.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://demo.stack.jimmycai.com/p/welcome-to-my-game-programming-blog/urbanstrikers_splitscreen.png"
width="1823"
height="1025"
srcset="https://demo.stack.jimmycai.com/p/welcome-to-my-game-programming-blog/urbanstrikers_splitscreen_hu_6ee2c82223a36c34.png 480w, https://demo.stack.jimmycai.com/p/welcome-to-my-game-programming-blog/urbanstrikers_splitscreen_hu_edccad1864981049.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Image of the game urban strikers. It has a horizontal splitscreen, with a player on top and bottom of the screen."
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="177"
data-flex-basis="426px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The game is available for free on itchio : &lt;a class="link" href="https://ratala321.itch.io/urban-strikers" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>https://ratala321.itch.io/urban-strikers&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Unreal Engine&lt;/strong> was used to make this game. Also, it was made during the &lt;a class="link" href="https://montreal.ubisoft.com/en/our-commitments/education/game-lab-competition/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>&lt;strong>2025 Ubisoft Gamelab&lt;/strong>&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="dreamland-bastion">Dreamland bastion
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>A turn-based tower defense online multiplayer game.&lt;br>
I&amp;rsquo;ve mostly worked as a programmer on all things related online, the building system and the game loop.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://demo.stack.jimmycai.com/p/welcome-to-my-game-programming-blog/dreamlandbastion-overview.png"
width="1918"
height="980"
srcset="https://demo.stack.jimmycai.com/p/welcome-to-my-game-programming-blog/dreamlandbastion-overview_hu_13ac0187b9f145af.png 480w, https://demo.stack.jimmycai.com/p/welcome-to-my-game-programming-blog/dreamlandbastion-overview_hu_347b6168b97095e.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Image of the game dreamland bastion. We can see three side by side boards. The players are on different boards."
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="195"
data-flex-basis="469px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The game is available for free on itchio : &lt;a class="link" href="https://harnm.itch.io/dreamland-bastion" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>https://harnm.itch.io/dreamland-bastion&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Unity&lt;/strong> was used to make this game. It was made during the &lt;a class="link" href="https://montreal.ubisoft.com/en/our-commitments/education/game-lab-competition/2024-edition/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>&lt;strong>2024 Ubisoft Gamelab&lt;/strong>&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-end">THE END
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>Thank you for reading through my first blog post !&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you have any feedbacks, comments or just need to vent, reach me at my email : talaia.gamedev(at)pm.me&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Archives</title><link>https://demo.stack.jimmycai.com/archives/</link><pubDate>Sun, 06 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://demo.stack.jimmycai.com/archives/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Links</title><link>https://demo.stack.jimmycai.com/links/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://demo.stack.jimmycai.com/links/</guid><description>&lt;!-- # Text could be here --></description></item><item><title>Search</title><link>https://demo.stack.jimmycai.com/search/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://demo.stack.jimmycai.com/search/</guid><description/></item></channel></rss>